Advertise your product or brand here
contact www.OpenSubtitles.org today
Many years later.
as he faced the firing squad...
Colonel Aureliano Buendía
was to remember that distant afternoon...
when his father took him to discover ice.
ONE HUNDRED YEARS OF SOLITUDE
José Arcadio Buendía
and Úrsula Iguarán were cousins.
They had grown up together
in the old village
their ancestors had transformed into
one of the finest towns in the province.
José Arcadio Buendía.
let Úrsula breathe for a second.
Just wait a little longer!
Let's celebrate. This is your party.
- Let's go. man. Come on.
- Let's go!
Although their marriage was predicted.
when they expressed their desire to wed.
their relatives tried to stop it.
They feared
that two healthy products of two races
interbred over the centuries
would suffer the shame
of breeding iguanas.
They would've been happy
if Úrsula's mother had not frightened her
with all manner of sinister predictions
about their offspring.
Hey! Come here!
What's this?
Mom gave it to me.
I can't believe she's still tormenting you
with superstitions
or that you even listen to her.
This isn't a superstition.
She told me something horrible.
What could be more horrible
than what you have on?
Bearing a monster.
My mother's cousins married
and had a deformed son.
He lived a life of shame because of that.
What kind of deformity?
He had a pig's tail.
A coiled intestine
with a hairy tip like a corkscrew.
Why would she make that up?
She told me he bled out
after they cut off his tail
with a cleaver.
I don't care if I have piglets
as long as they can talk.
I do care.
I will not bear pigs!
During the day.
he would take care of his fighting cocks.
and she would embroider.
At night. they would wrestle
for hours in an anguished violence
that seemed to be
a substitute for the act of love.
José Arcadio Buendía and Úrsula Iguarán
lived like that for several months.
I didn't think you'd come.
I bet on your rooster. Is he ready?
I brought him
because he's ready. my friend.
Magnífico. how are the odds?
- José. they have faith in you. as always.
- There you are. Buendía!
You've waited so long to face me.
only to be defeated today.
Unbelievable!
I hope you like chicken soup
because he's a goner.
You hear me?
Come on!
Peck him! That's it!
Kill him!
Peck him!
Kill him! Get him!
Kill him!
Peck him!
Come on. damn it! Get him! Do it!
That's it! Kill him!
Get up!
Come on! Get up!
My rooster!
Let's go.
Look. my friend. that's life.
You have a good animal. Congratulations.
Come here. beautiful.
Hey. Buendía!
Maybe that rooster of yours
can do your wife a favor.
Go home and get a weapon.
I'm going to kill you.
He's angry.
What's the matter with you?
- It was great.
- True.
José Arcadio.
José Arcadio!
If you bear iguanas. we'll raise iguanas.
But there'll be no more deaths
in this town because of us.
As the senior officials of this town.
the mayor and I have reached a conclusion.
While the death
of Prudencio Aguilar is a tragedy.
we have found
that it was the result of a duel of honor.
Therefore. the honorable
José Arcadio Buendía
has been found not guilty.
- No!
- That's not fair!
Outrageous!
Enough! Show some decorum!
Well done. Thank you.
You just need a few drinks
to put all this behind you.
What are you doing here?
You know you asked for it.
Go to hell.
If you keep coming back.
I'll just keep killing you.
José Arcadio Buendía
did not dare throw his spear.
and Prudencio Aguilar did not go away.
They never had peace after that.
They were tormented
by the immense desolation
with which the dead man
had looked at them that night...
his deep nostalgia
as he yearned for living people...
the anxiety
with which he searched the house
looking for some water
to soak his esparto plug.
Úrsula was so moved after seeing
the dead man uncovering the pots
that she placed water jugs
all over the house.
What do I have to do for you to go away?
It's all right. Prudencio.
We're going to get as far away
from this town as we can.
and we'll never come back.
Where will we go?
We'll find the sea beyond the mountains.
That's absurd.
No one has made that journey.
Exactly.
We'll find a place
where the fears of our ancestors
won't weigh us down.
Where we can love each other in peace...
and raise a family.
The sea.
Thanks. Dad.
Goodbye. Mom.
Úrsula...
no matter where you go...
you will never escape your fate.
Take care of yourselves.
Let's go. friend.
That was how they undertook
crossing the mountains.
Several friends of José Arcadio Buendía.
young men like him.
excited by the adventure.
packed up with their wives and children
to head toward the land
that no one had promised them.
Danger.
The Hanged Man sees the world differently.
Has she read the cards to you?
She has for some time.
Thank you.
Big push!
One more! Push!
Hard! Here it comes!
With her stomach ravaged
by monkey meat and snake stew.
Úrsula gave birth to a son
who was all human.
with the help of Pilar Ternera.
Let's go!
Whoa! Easy!
Easy. boy!
Stop him!
Come on. Geri.
Don't worry. Gerineldo.
We're close to the sea now.
One morning.
after almost two years of crossing.
they became the first mortals to witness
the western slope of the mountain range.
From the cloudy summit.
they saw the immense aquatic expanse
of the great swamp
as it spread toward
the other side of the world.
But they never saw the sea.
- Where the hell is the sea?! Where is it?!
- Hey! Cut it out!
Gerineldo. calm down!
It must be beyond the great swamp.
Hey!
Stop. please!
Stop!
We're walking in circles.
He has no fucking idea where we are.
We need to find our way by land.
One afternoon.
after several months
of lost wandering through the swamps.
they camped on the banks of a stony river
whose waters
were like a torrent of frozen glass.
The great swamp has to end somewhere.
We need to find a way to get
to the other side and reach the sea.
José Arcadio Buendía.
it's time to get out of your head.
Have you seen the state of your people?
José Arcadio Buendía dreamed that night
that a noisy city rose up there...
with houses that had mirrored walls.
He asked what city it was.
and they answered him
with a name that he had never heard.
that had no meaning at all...
but had a supernatural echo in his dream...
Macondo.
Come on.
Gerineldo...
I know we haven't found the sea
or a place to live.
but it's ludicrous to keep searching.
Everybody is free
to choose their own path...
but we're going to stay here.
We'll build the place we've dreamed of.
The home of our children.
A place where no one can decide
for others. Not even how they die.
And this place...
shall be known as Macondo.
José Arcadio. why are you naked?
Go back home.
Macondo was a village
of 20 houses made of adobe and reeds.
built on the bank of a clear water river
that ran along a bed of polished stones.
white and enormous. like prehistoric eggs.
- Hi. Daddy!
- My boy!
The world was so new
that many things lacked names.
To mention them. you had to point.
José Arcadio!
Sweetie. give these corozos to your mom
so she can make you some juice.
Thank you.
José Arcadio Buendía
had set the houses up in such a way
that from each one.
you could reach the river
and draw water equally.
He had arranged the streets
with such good sense
that no house got more sun
during the heat of the day.
- Hi. Mommy.
- Naked again?
Have you no shame?
And these corozos?
Do you want some juice?
All right. Come on.
Look!
It's beautiful.
- Where is it going to live?
- Come on.
The little birdie will live here.
Over the following years.
José Arcadio Buendía filled
with troupials. canaries.
bluebirds. and robins.
not only in his own house
but all in the village.
The chorus of so many birds
became so disorienting
that Úrsula would plug her ears
with beeswax
to not lose her sense of reality.
Put that over there.
Úrsula!
A bed.
It's comfortable.
Let's try it out.
Right now?
What was that?
Who are you?
My name is Melquiades.
And this is my family.
Our fair comes from afar.
How did you find us?
The birds.
We've been traveling
through the great swamp
and were drawn to their song.
It's a pleasure to meet you.
I am José Arcadio Buendía...
and Macondo is the name of this town.
Ladies and gentlemen.
we've brought to these faraway lands
the eighth wonder
of the sage alchemists of Macedonia.
For all who wish to witness
this extraordinary invention.
come with me. please.
Today you shall see things come to life.
It's just a matter
of awakening their souls.
That's witchcraft!
No. ma'am.
It's science.
And if you want to see more.
you're all welcome to visit our fair.
José Arcadio Buendía.
whose unbridled imagination
always went beyond the genius of nature.
miracles. and magic.
thought it was possible
to use that useless invention
to extract gold from the earth.
You're not taking them.
But metals are drawn to those things.
And we need goats for sustenance.
Can't you see
that we could be full of gold?
What good is gold in this town?
Darling.
Macondo won't stay like this forever.
We need to think about the future.
I'm afraid I can't sell you the magnets
for that purpose.
Your logic makes sense.
but paradoxically.
precious metals are not drawn to them.
It may not work with small quantities...
but I'm sure it'll work
to unearth large rocks
or entire treasures.
I can pay for them.
I cannot sell them
in good conscience. believe me.
You'd lose your investment.
Let me see that for myself.
You have nothing to lose.
Very well.
I like your enthusiasm.
Gerineldo. what are you doing?
We already tried here. Look over there.
Why didn't you tell me that earlier?
That's obvious. You're an idiot.
- Stay there. I'll look.
- Fine. Get back to work.
Hey! Come here!
It has to be something big.
A dead man.
The only thing we were able to find
after a week is a damn dead guy.
Where is all that gold
you were going to dig up?
You have to bring the goats back.
They're no longer ours.
If you won't talk
to that cheating gypsy. I will.
We can't afford to give our animals away.
Much less now.
Much less now?
I'm pregnant.
Wonderful news.
My wife doesn't even want them
in the house.
At least you saw it for yourself.
Experience... is everything in life.
Feel free to take your goats.
They're waiting for you.
Melquiades...
can I ask you something?
Of course.
How did you not get lost in those swamps?
They're treacherous.
It was a long and difficult journey.
but our instruments always guided us.
What instruments?
Just a moment.
Look. This right here is an astrolabe.
For centuries. humans have tried to study
the skies to understand Earth.
Here.
Science is eliminating distance.
Look. This is a compass.
And a sextant.
Before long.
man will be able to see what is going on
anywhere in the world
without leaving home.
Portuguese maps. They're old.
Look.
This will help you learn how to use them.
They're yours.
Thank you. Melquiades.
On that day.
José Arcadio Buendía had the certainty
that it was the beginning
of a great friendship.
He spent entire nights
watching the course of the stars.
When he became an expert in the use
and manipulation of his instruments.
he conceived a notion of space
that allowed him to navigate unknown seas.
visit inhabited territories.
and establish relationships
with splendid beings.
I don't know what you're doing
with those maps. but do it elsewhere.
I want to understand where Macondo is
to see if I can finally find
a path to civilization.
I know the answer.
Macondo is here.
and your head is in the clouds.
José Arcadio. time to eat!
Wash your hands first. They're dirty.
Let's go.
Goodbye. Dad!
Goodbye. my son!
This ship must be about 200 years old.
It has to be close.
What has to be close?
The sea!
That discovery broke
José Arcadio Buendía's spirit.
He considered it a trick of his fate
to have searched for the sea
without finding it.
after many sacrifices.
and to have found it
without looking for it.
We gave up
just before finding the sea. Úrsula.
Macondo is surrounded by water.
We took several measurements.
but we need more to complete the map.
We need to go on another expedition.
We need to contact the world.
You can't leave again.
José Arcadio Buendía.
Can't you see that we need you?
José Arcadio.
Listen.
What is that?
Come here.
Listen.
The baby's crying in my belly.
Matilda. the compresses!
- Hurry!
- I'm here!
Breathe! Take deep breaths!
Don't push. Just breathe.
Úrsula shuddered from the certainty
that the deep howl
was the first indication
of the fearful pig tail.
She begged God
to let the creature die in her womb.
You're almost there.
Here it comes!
Come on! One more! That's it!
Aureliano was the first human
to be born in Macondo.
He was born with his eyes open.
examining the world
with an indifferent curiosity.
Úrsula did not remember
the intensity of that look again
until years later
when. one afternoon. Aureliano Buendía
had his first premonition.
Mom. the pot is going to fall.
The pot's fine. Aureliano.
When he had begun
to be aware of his premonitions.
Colonel Aureliano Buendía thought
that death would be announced
with a definite. unequivocal.
irrevocable signal.
But just moments before his death...
the signal had not come.
BASED ON THE NOVEL
BY GABRIEL GARCÍA MÁRQUEZ
Subtitle translation by: Alison Woods
Support us and become VIP member
to remove all ads from www.OpenSubtitles.org